I've been watching the encroaching
attacks on women's rights in this
country for the last few months and
personally it's just something that I
cannot stand to watch on the sidelines
anymore so I decided to make this video
to share with you some of the insights
that I have into how this war on women
has come to be and what we can do about
it so we really have to go back several
centuries to understand how this all
began back in the dark ages there was
this period of time where dogmatic
fundamentalist thinking was the
grounding for preserving a system of
patriarchy and control and dominance by
men over women something that had been
happening for a very long time and that
began to lose its hold on society in the
enlightenment era in the 1600s and 1700s
when there was a growing trend of
secularization that placed dogmatic
views about the role of an authoritarian
God on society put that on the sideline
and started to elevate a different view
of human nature the places reasoning in
the capacity for people to consider
their own options and make their own
choices as something that increasingly
became a centerpiece of society now the
secularization threatened the
fundamentalist view which is profoundly
patriarchal and authoritarian this
happened in many ways it rose with the
increase of literacy and the printing of
books that allowed people to seek their
own questions and answers about matters
that previously have been the realm of
authority of an impure and empirical
arms or an imperial church and as the
rights of citizens start to became
recognized as something that could
displace the authoritarian centrality of
of church as the mode of government in
the world there began to have a
liberalisation a process of increasing
freedom that was based in a sense of
empathy and compassion for others that
people increasingly saw as being
themselves this is what led to women's
suffrage in the right to vote it's what
gave us the expanding freedoms that
ended slavery and started to bring more
inclusivity to people from different
races and cultures as we increased and
expanded our capacity for inclusiveness
in the societies that we lived in now
this is something that's really become
an acute conflict in the modern world
where the historic conservative
patriarchal authoritarian view has
corroded as there's been an increasing
acceptance of the basic dignity and
respect for all human beings and an
inclusivity that enables us to consider
how women should be empowered in society
of course this is something that in
today's world in politics we see express
through the label of conservatism in the
United States now why is it that
conservatism is so deeply maligned so
antithetical to women's rights in modern
society we'll simply put conservatism is
a world of you that's based in
authoritarianism the top-down hierarchy
and its central governing principle is
that the sanctity of authority must be
preserved at all costs now in the
context of Western religion this is most
pronounced and religious fundamentalism
in Christianity in Judaism and even in
Islam where it's a fundamentalist view
but always it's something that is
grounded and a notion that there is a
vengeful God who is a male God who has
dominance over the world and women must
know their place in the moral order and
so now the men of this movement to
protect to protect fundamentalism in the
world are seeking to stamp out the
rights of women to preserve that moral
order the moral order simply is the
notion that there is a vertical
hierarchy where God is above humans men
are above women humanity's above nature
and in some cases it's even still racist
that whites are above non-white
and that Westerners are above mom
Westerners but it's really most acute in
society today with the relationship
between men and women in their place in
society now something that's really
fundamental to this psychologically
that's happening right now is that these
these patriarchal authoritarians you go
by the name of conservative are actually
acting like bullies in society they're
pushing their views around they're
beating people up verbally emotionally
and in some cases physically through the
taking away of basic rights of people
and something that you may not know is
that the historic evolutionary roots of
democracy in humanity actually come from
that the way that groups of people
handle bullies so if you go back to the
hunter-gatherer days where we lived in
small bands of between 50 and 200 people
group cohesion was absolutely essential
for the survival of those groups and so
the capacity for those groups to stop
bullies from being the would-be upstarts
basically from stop them from becoming
dictators and siphoning valuable
resources away from the group for their
own gain became the central tenant of
what later emerged as the expression of
democracy so democracy at its very core
is the power of the group to stop
bullies from throwing their weight
around and doing harm to the group at
the expense of the group and so this war
on women is really right at the core a
battle for democracy so this is
something that goes way back to our
evolutionary origins to the birth of
society itself is how do groups of
people handle bullies when bullies are
trying to throw their weight around and
do harm to the group for personal gain
so when we're talking about the rights
of women in this conversation we're
really talking about the heart of
democracy if we cannot treat women while
in society then we can't treat anything
that has to do with democracy in a way
that's actually going to be effective
so what can we do about these bullies
who have a patriarchal authoritarian
view of the world well first of all the
way to stop a bully is to call them out
to publicly shame them to say no more we
will not accept this this is just as
true for the way that we handle say a
bully on the playground beating up
another kid or the way that homophobic
people bully young homosexual children
or teenage boys and girls who happen to
be gay and we've seen what's happened in
that situation where these gay boys and
girls who are bullied commit suicide and
then we've had these huge anti-bullying
rallies well it's time to have just the
same kind of anti-bullying rallies
against the patriarchal authoritarians
these people who think that men should
have demanded dominion over women and
that democracy has no place in society
those people need to be shut down and
stopped we need to publicly shame them
and say this is unacceptable in our
world in America today also we need to
call out that this is actually an
outdated view of the world that this
religious fundamentalism is something
that thrived in the dark ages but has no
place in the modern era and the reason
that it's raising its ugly head right
now is because it feels threatened this
fundamentalism and it's patriarchy views
or being challenged by increasing
modernism and globalization and the
expansion of human rights so this is our
time to call it out and say this is the
21st century world we shouldn't be
basing how we treat people in society on
the dictates of a moral code that are
hundreds of years old and in some sense
even thousands of years old now is the
time for us to focus on how to live in a
deeply interconnected and pluralistic
world where we have to live with people
who have different views from ourselves
we have to have tolerance and acceptance
also we have to deal with global
systemic threats so we have to live and
embrace live in and embrace the
complexities of the modern world so the
archaic notions of authoritarianism from
a past
are not going to serve us today so
fundamentalism needs to be held in place
and treated as the bullying that it
truly is so what will happen if we're
successful at doing this well simply put
we will be able to restore democracy to
its central place in American society
and increasingly in the world which is
where it belongs so this is a time for
us to call out the extremism in our
political parties and of course this is
an unbalanced equation the Republican
Party has been taken over at the highest
levels by these radical extremists
authoritarians and they are now
espousing a fundamentalist view onto
society which really has hints of things
that we could even call in a legitimate
technical way we could call them fascism
how a dictator kind of mindset is being
used to oppress the masses to advance
its own view and consolidate power and
this is happening in the alignment of
religious fundamentalism with particular
kinds of corporate governance and that
we're seeing that in the world today so
this is our chance to put an end to that
by rallying together around calling out
how basic human rights for half of our
species for all of the women in the
world are being threatened in a
fundamental way and so if we can
actually turn the tide on this
conversation change the discourse we can
elevate the discussion of what democracy
is and should be how bullies should be
treated in society and what we as if
people want to do in our 21st century
world and of course now is the time to
take action we saw earlier this year
what happened when Rush Limbaugh started
bullying and upstanding young woman he
called her a slut he called her a
prostitute he even went so far as to
suggest that if she wants to have sex
and have contraception covered by
medical insurance that she should film
it and he and other patriarchal men can
watch her sexual encounters as
pornography talk about disgusting and
the amazing thing is the response that
came from that as women around the world
use social media to rally themselves and
to bring the men who cared about them
and you agreed with them too
cause it was real women leadership
female leadership that caused this to
happen and they initiated a boycott
against Rush Limbaugh and I don't know
if you know this but for the first time
in the history of Rush Limbaugh Show
there was actually a blackout during
advertising a 30-second window of time
where there was silence because they
weren't able to get enough advertisers
to pay for commercials that shows that
they are weak that they're on the
defensive and so now is the time to go
after them and to beat them back down we
collectively need to put a stop to this
kind of bullying and if we do we can
return the focus of this country in its
national discourse to where it belongs
which is focusing on how to build and
preserve complex economies and address
really difficult problems like changing
climate and the spread of disease and
public health and how to live in a
pluralistic world all these things that
we know we need to be dealing with and
get away from all these distractions
that these bullies are making us focus
on which is both wasting our time and
hurting our democracy so this is what is
happening in the world today this war on
women goes way back you can follow the
trends throughout the entire modern era
of an expansion of compassion and
freedom and how does a pushback against
it and if we act collectively now and if
we stand up and claim our rights and our
need for a real democracy in the 21st
century we can actually win so let's do
it